Preliminary Guide to the School of Engineering Records, 1931-2014 UA.21.01.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
School of Engineering records
1931 - 2014
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. School of Engineering
UA.21.01.0001
50 Linear Feet
Contains the records of the School of Engineering at Duke University from 1931 to 2014. Includes records of the Department of Electrical Engineering, Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering, Engineering Student Government, and the Engineering Alumni Association. Type of materials include biographical files, general subject files, correspondence, photographs, clippings, rosters, minutes, reports, proposals, course descriptions, memoirs, honors, and vitae. Major subjects include Duke University, students, School of Engineering, the study and teaching of science and engineering, and scientific research. English.
Access Restrictions
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
Conditions Governing Access
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Conditions Governing Access
Electronic records in this collection have been migrated to a library server and digital use copies can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library Reading Room. To request access, please contact a reference archivist before coming to use these records.
Conditions Governing Access
Records, such as search committee files or others pertaining to employment where individuals are identified, are closed for 70 years.
Provenance
Received 1976. School of Engineering, Subject files of Associate Dean Edward K. Kraybill. Accession number: 76-32 (Boxes 1-6)
Received 1976. School of Engineering, Subject files of Dean Charles R. Vail. Accession number: 76-32 (Boxes 7-15)
Received 1978 and 1983. School of Engineering, Office of the Dean, alphabetical subject files. Accession numbers: A83-62, A78-143 (Boxes 16-28)
Received 1989. School of Engineering, Office of the Dean, faculty and staff biographical files. Accession numbers: A89-006 (Box 29)
Received 1993 and 1996. School of Engineering, Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering. Accession numbers: A93-24, A93-98, 96-107. Also received 1982. Engineering Student Government. Accession numbers: A82-41 (Box 30)
Received 1984, 1985, 1988, 1991, 1999. School of Engineering, Department of Electrical Engineering. Accession numbers: A84-14, A85-93, A88-038, A91-62, A99-36 (Box 31)
Received 1977, 1979, 1994. School of Engineering, Engineering Alumni Association. Accession numbers: A77-27, A79-21, A94-115, A94-132 (Boxes 32-33)
Received 1983. School of Engineering, Office of the Dean, alphabetical subject files. Accession numbers: A83-62 (Boxes 34-36)
Received 2015. Pratt School of Engineering, 75th anniversary video files. Accession number UA2015.0004
Historical Note
From http://www.ee.duke.edu/graduate/abouteng.html
The School of Engineering traces its history back to 1851 when the catalogue for Normal College, the forerunner of Trinity College and Duke University, advertised a Classical course which included surveying in the sophomore year as well as architecture and engineering for seniors. Similar offerings characterized instruction in the subject of engineering throughout the 73 year period of the institution's operation as Trinity College. When Trinity College because Duke University in 1924, Engineering instruction underwent a period of vigorous development.
The School of Engineering at Duke is currently primarily housed in its own two buildings: Hudson Hall (fondly known as Old Red) and the modern Teer Building. It also shares space with other science facilities in the Levine Science Research Center which is separate from the Engineering Buildings. The School of Engineering is composed of the four departments of Electrical and Computer Engineering, Biomedical Engineering, Civil and Environmental Engineering, and Mechanical Engineering and Materials Science. There are also shared research facilities and joint research activities with numerous other departments including Physics, Computer Science, Mathematics and Medicine.
The School of Engineering houses the prestigious National Science Foundation Center for Advanced Cardiovascular Technology, which is an international leader in the application of Engineering to Medicine, and the Vesic Engineering Library in the Teer Building.
Related Material
DukEngineer [serial].
University Archives, Duke University.
Report to the National Science Foundation covering development grant GE 2558 to the School of Engineering, Duke University, June 29, 1963-December 31, 1967. Submitted by J. L. Meriam, 1968.
University Archives, Duke University.
School of Engineering, reference collection
University Archives, Duke University.
Small Collections, School of Engineering, Engineering Club
University Archives, Duke University.
Biró, Péter. Means Without End: the Birth of the Duke School of Engineering 1887-1966, 1991.
University Archives, Duke University
Duke University. Task Force on Science and Engineering. Report of the Task Force on Science and Engineering at Duke University: submitted to the Provost, May 5, 1994, 1994.
University Archives, Duke University
Collection Overview
Contains the records of the School of Engineering pertaining to courses of instruction, employees, research, students, and general management. Materials in subject files are roughly organized by topics. Engineering Alumni files are largely unordered. Faculty and staff biographical files are ordered alphabetically by last name. Some boxes are restricted.
Engineering students -- United States; Environmental engineering; Graduate students in science -- United States; Graduate students in engineering -- United States; Science -- Study and teaching -- North Carolina -- Durham; Science -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- United States; Civil Engineering -- North Carolina; Electric engineering; Engineering -- Study and teaching (Graduate) -- United States; Engineering -- Study and teaching -- North Carolina -- Durham; Duke University; Duke University. School of Engineering -- History; Duke University -- Students; Duke University. Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering; Duke University. Department of Electrical Engineering; Duke University. Engineering Alumni Association -- Directories; Duke University. School of Engineering -- Alumni and alumnae -- Directories
- Accession number: A76-32
  - Academic planning - Alumni (engineering), nominating committee (Box 1)
  - Alumni (engineering), off-campus meetings - Curriculum committee and instruction committee (Box 2)
  - Curriculum, undergraduate - Engineering Student Government, newsletters (Box 3)
  - Faculty files, advising, - Phi Eta Sigma (Box 4)
    Scope and Contents note
    Including lectures, personnel.
  - Matthews, Ralph T. - Science fairs (Box 5)
  - Slide Rules, Scientific, and Educational Equipment - Committee on undergraduate colleges (Box 6)
    Includes correspondence.
  - Academic Standards Committee meetings - American Institute of Electrical Engineers (AIEE) (Box 7)
  - AIEE recognition awards - Clippings and College of Engineering, general (Box 8)
  - Counseling, Bureau of Testing and Guidance Material and general Engineering program, Development Program (Box 9)
  - Development Program (Box 10)
  - Development Program - Graduate Program (Box 11)
  - Graduate Administration, Research program - National Science Foundation (Box 12)
  - Patent Policy committee - Research Triangle Institute (Box 13)
  - Research Triangle Institute - Special Programs, Western Electric (Box 14)
  - Special Programs, Western Electric - Visiting Engineers, includes Staff, general (Box 15)
- Accession numbers: A83-62, A78-143
  - Academic Council - Course evaluation (Box 16)
    Includes Driver Education Research and Training, Admissions Office, ASDU, Board of Visitors, Engineering Alumni Association.
  - Engineering building, faculty - Institute of Policy Sciences (Box 17)
    Includes engineering faculty (1971-1975), engineering student government, graduate studies, high school symposium.
  - Interdisciplinary programs - proposal on Interdisciplinary Program (Box 18)
    Includes minority applicants, patent policy, orientation, promotion and tenure
  - News clippings books - University Science Development proposals (Box 19)
    Includes A Plan of Action, faculty research, 1971-1976.
  - Provost Council - Women in Engineering (Box 20)
    Includes sponsored research, symposium, traffic commission, trustees.
  - ECPD Accreditation Visit, BME, CE, EE, ME, 1973 (Box 21)
  - Faculty meeting minutes, 1972-1980 (Box 22)
    MacElduff retirement memory book, includes some publications and ECPD accreditation
  - Policy on University travel - Policies, School of Engineering (Box 23)
    Includes summaries of sponsored research, research history, long range planning, development of Engineering at Duke University, Board of Visitors.
  - ASCE (American Society of Civil Engineers) - Undergraduate planning information (Box 24)
    Includes ECPD, PENC, accreditation for civil engineering, Engineers Joint Council, Phi Beta Kappa, Pi Tau Sigma.
  - ASEE - RANN, National Science Foundation information (Box 25)
    Includes Self-study (1965), ECPD (1971-1979), and NC Board of Science and Technology.
  - Faculty census forms, 1970-1981 (Box 26)
  - Research activity, 1977-1979 (Box 26)
  - Engineering Faculty Council, 1953-1978 (Box 27)
    Includes bound volumes of Executive Committee and Administrative Council meeting minutes
  - Includes Dean's reports, NROTC, student lounge, Development Program, aeronautics, Engineer's Show (presented by students), 1939-1964 (Box 28)
- Accession number: A89-006
  Conditions Governing Access
  Personnel information is restricted for 70 years from date of creation; material must be screened before use.
  - Biographical files of Engineering faculty and employees (Box 29)
    Includes vitae, clippings, photographs, proposals, and some correspondence.
- Accession numbers: A93-24, A93-98, 96-107, A82-41; Restricted
  - Engineering Student Government records, 1931-1979. (Box 30)
    Includes minutes, correspondence, Engineer's Show notes, West Campus Community Council
  - Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering records, 1936-1999. (Box 30)
    Includes minutes, correspondence, reports, student papers, subject files, notes of research activity, and faculty meeting minutes.
- Accession numbers: A84-14, A85-93, A88-038, A91-62, A99-36
  - Department of Electrical Engineering, 1946-1972 (Box 31)
    Includes minutes, correspondence, reports, student papers, memos, grant reports, reports of research activities, and Babbling Brooks newsletter for Engineering Alumni.
- Accession numbers: A77-27, A79-21, A94-115, A94-132
  - School of Engineering, Engineering Alumni Association, 1954-1994 (Box 32)
    Includes Alumni Council meeting minutes, honorary degrees.
  - School of Engineering, Engineering Alumni Association, 1954-1994 (Box 33)
    Includes 50th reunion directory, awards, newsletters, Alumni Council meeting minutes, some correspondence to alumni
  - School of Engineering, Engineering Alumni Association, 1954-1994 (Box 37)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes "Southgate Memories" illustrations and photocopies of Durham Herald-Sun front page from December 7, 1941.
- Accession numbers: A83-62
  - Publications from engineering firms, ca. 1970-1979 (Box 34)
  - Engineering building annex parking lot, 1976-1979 (Box 34)
  - Renovations, 1976-1978 (Box 34)
  - Building plans and proposals (Box 34)
  - Duke University Construction Program reports (Box 34)
  - Committee and subject files A-L (Box 34)
  - Committee and subject files L-Z (Box 35)
  - Laboratories mechanics and space needs (Box 35)
  - Building Committee meetings, notes, and subcommittee materials (Box 35)
  - Associates, contractors, files, ca. 1965-1970 (Box 35)
  - Correspondence, October 1981-June 1982 (Box 36)
  - Biofeedback Laboratory (Box 36)
  - Women and Minorities in the School of Engineering, files and reports, ca. 1974-1977 (Box 36)
  - Governance and management of the School of Engineering, files and reports, ca. 1976-1979 (Box 36)
- Accession number: UA2015.0004 (Box 36, Item UA21010001-USB-01)
  This accession includes a video commemorating the School of Engineering's 75 anniversary as well as original interview footage with four Deans of the School used in the final video. Interview footage consists of unedited interview footage with Deans George W. Pearsall, Earl Dowell, Kristina Johnson, and Tom Katsouleas, discussing the history, characteristics, and future of the School of Engineering at Duke. The final video includes edited footage from these interviews as well as interviews with other persons closely associated with the School and historic photographs, tracing the history and accomplishments of the School of Engineering.
  Access Restrictions
  Electronic records in this collection have been migrated to a library server and digital use copies can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library Reading Room. To request access, please contact a reference archivist before coming to use these records.
  - Duke Engineering: 75 Years Rising, 2014; 151 Megabytes (Video-file UA210101-MP4-001)
    Video is 10 minutes, 56 seconds long.
  - Interview with Dean Earl Dowell, unedited, 2014; 1270 Megabytes (Video-file UA210101-M4V-001)
    Video is 35 minutes, 27 seconds long.
  - Interview with Dean Kristina Johnson, unedited, 2014; 767 Megabytes (Video-file UA210101-M4V-002)
    Video is 20 minutes, 54 seconds long.
  - Interview with Dean Tom Katsouleas, unedited, 2014; 1420 Megabytes (Video-file UA210101-M4V-003)
    Video is 39 minutes, 37 seconds long.
  - Interview with Dean George W. Pearsall, unedited, 2014; 2030 Megabytes (Video-file UA210101-M4V-004)
    Video is 56 minutes, 41 seconds long.